<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
      <!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
    <document>
  
    <header><title>Getting Started</title></header>
      
  
  <body>
    <section id="overview"><title>Overview</title>
      <p> Although some software is available, XLattice is still in the
        discussion and planning stage.  The overall architecture is 
        not completely settled, and the current interface is almost
        certainly very much unlike what it will eventually become.
        The software that exists is there for talking and thinking
        about.</p>

      <p>There are basically two ways to get XLattice - and most other open
        source software.  The first is CVS, which gives you access to 
        last night's version of the code.  The second is to download the 
        latest release.  This is more likely to work, but is less up to date;
        current plans are to put out incremental XLattice releases at 
        roughly monthly intervals.</p>
      
      <p>XLattice is being developed on systems running Linux and FreeBSD.
        If you are working under a Microsoft operating system, you may
        need to use some initiative to get the advice that follows to
        work.  We will try to improve on this situation; please be 
        patient.</p>

      <p><strong>The instructions that follow are suitable for downloading the
            Java implementation of XLattice to Linux hosts.</strong></p>

      <section id="CVSAccess"><title>CVS Access</title>
        <p>XLattice is hosted on 
          <a href="http://www.sourceforge.net">SourceForge.</a>
          On Unix systems, 
          you can get a copy of the most recent version of an XLattice 
          compenent by typing:
        </p>
<source>
cvs -d:pserver:anonymous@cvs.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/xlattice checkout module
</source>
        <p>where <strong><em>module</em></strong> represents the component name.</p>
        
        <p>This will deliver the very latest version to your desktop,
          creating a <strong>xlattice</strong> subdirectory in the current 
          directory if one does not already exist, with the module
          in a subdirectory below that.</p>

        <p>If you are using another operating system, or have trouble
          with the instructions above, have a look at 
          <a href="http://sourceforge.net/docman/display_doc.php?docid=14033&amp;group_id=1">Sourceforge's CVS documentation</a>;
          this is lucid and reasonably easy to follow.</p>
      </section>

      <section id="Downloads"><title>Downloads</title>
        <p>The alternative is downloading a release.  This is very
          simple indeed.  You should see a <strong>Download</strong> button at
          the top of this Web page; if you click on it, it will take
          you to XLattice's Sourceforge download page.  The most recent
          releases will be listed towards the top.</p>
        <p>XLattice is divided into a number of components.  Each is
          released as a zip file containing any jars necessary for 
          the build, source code, javadocs, and the jar for the 
          release.</p>
        <p>The util-0.1 release, for example, is packaged
          as util-0.1.zip.  This unzips into a local 
          ./xlattice subdirectory.  xlattice/lib
          contains the jars, including the release, which is to be found
          in xlattice/lib/xlattice/util-0.1.jar.</p>

          <p>Click on whichever release
            you need, and your browser will get it for you.</p>

        <p>Once you have the tarball, put it in the directory where
          you want your XLattice subdirectory and type </p>
<source>
  unzip util-0.1.zip
</source>
        <p>(replacing the actual component name and version number
          as appropriate) and it will be extracted for you.  
            </p><p>These instructions 
            are of course suitable for Linux/Unix hosts; if you are 
            using Windows, you need to adjust appropriately.</p>
      </section>

      <section id="WherestheJar"><title>Where's the Jar?</title>
        <p>Either of the procedures above will give you a distribution
          in a subdirectory named  xlattice and the jar
          in xlattice/lib/xlattice along with a copy of
          the XLattice license.</p>

        <p>Other jars are in similarly-named subdirectories.  The
          Ant jars, for example, are under xlattice/lib/ant.</p>

      </section>

      <section id="ForDevelopers"><title>For Developers</title>
        <p>Those with an interest in XLattice's inner workings might
          be interested in getting 
          the software using CVS.  There are sometimes several 
        file changes a day.</p>

      <p>Once you have the software, you should go into the 
        XLattice directory for the component and run the tests.</p>  
      
<source>
  cd xlattice/utl
  ./build.sh test
</source>
      <p>These should execute with no or very few errors.  If you
        do see serious errors, it is likely that there are problems
        with the installation.</p>

      <p>The most likely problems are classpath errors and missing
        jar files.</p>
      </section>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
