<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
      <!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header><title>News/Changes</title></header>
  <body>
    <table>
        <tr><td>2007-07-10</td>
          <td><strong>corexml-0.3.5 release</strong>
            <p>We add NameGenerator to corexml.bind.  This is a facility 
              for generating class, method, and variable names in a 
              standardized way.  These names are to be used in various 
              types of automatically generated code, as for example in 
              other bind methods; in XLattice's ProjMgr component; and 
              in the forthcoming JAppGen J2EE MVC application generator 
              project, jappgen.sourceforge.net.
            </p></td></tr>
        <tr><td>2007-07-10</td>
          <td><strong>util-0.3.9 release</strong>
            <p>This release adds ucFirst and lcFirst methods to StringLib. 
              These are used fairly heavily by upcoming corexml and projmgr 
              component releases, which are in turn used by the JAppGen J2EE 
              MVC application generator, about to become available in alpha 
              at jappgen.sourceforge.net.
            </p></td></tr>
        <tr><td>2006-06-21</td>
          <td><strong>corexml-0.3.4</strong>
            <p>This is a minor release.  context/ has been moved to the util 
              component, and necessary changes in code have been made.  
              We switch to using junit-4.1 for testing, in line with the 
              earlier switch to Java 1.5.  And the release is now packaged as a ZIP file instead of a UNIX tarball.</p>
              
            <p>As usual, we include source code for this component and jars 
              for all dependencies.
            </p></td></tr>
        <tr><td>2006-06-21</td>
          <td><strong>projmgr-0.4.0</strong>
            <p>ProjMgr's first update in a couple of years sees util/context/ 
              replacing corexml/context/, JUnit updated to 4.1, and the use 
              of Java 1.5.  We also relax restrictions on version numbers; 
              any JNLP version number is now acceptable.  Finally, a number 
              of minor bugs have been fixed.</p>
              
            <p>This is a clean-up preparatory to using ProjMgr for
              project management (meaning largely automatic generation 
              of configuration
              files) in the soon-to-be released JAppGen  project.</p>

            <p>As usual, the .ZIP file includes source code for this 
              component (ProjMgr) and jars for all dependencies.
            </p></td></tr>
        <tr><td>2006-06-19</td>
          <td><strong>util-0.3.8</strong>
            <p>v0.3.8 makes minor changes to fundamental XLattice classes, 
              including Transport, Peer, and NodeID. We switch to using 
              JUnit 4.1 for unit testing. The release is now packaged as 
              a ZIP file instead of a UNIX tarball. 
            </p></td></tr>
        <tr><td>2006-06-15</td>
          <td><strong>crypto-0.1.2 release</strong>
            <p>This release adds TLS contexts and sessions which considerably 
              reduce the effort required to implement peer-to-peer TLS 
              connections between XLattice Nodes as well as SSL connections 
              between XLattice-based HTTP clients and servers.
            </p></td></tr>
        <tr><td>2006-06-04</td>
          <td><strong>crypto-0.1.1 release, switch to Java 1.5</strong>
            <p>Today's crypto-0.1.1 release improves the implementation of 
              SignedLists and adds the TLSEngine which will be used as the 
              basis for most node-to-node communications in XLattice networks.
            </p><p>This is our first release using features of Java 1.5.
            Excepting only the CryptoServer, all code in CVS has now been 
            tested using Java 1.5.  All future releases will assume Java 1.5 
            or better.
            </p></td></tr>
        <tr><td>2006-05-24</td>
          <td><strong>node-0.1.0</strong>
            <p>This is the first release of XLattice's node component.  A node is
              the key building block in our approach to peer-to-peer networking.
              A node has a cryptographic identity (an RSA key and a 160-bit
              SHA1-derived node ID) and can communicate with other nodes through
              one or more overlays.  An overlay is a combination of a transport,
              a protocol, and an address space.  Nodes from this first release
              communicate using TLS/SSL and UDP.
            </p><p>This release includes source code for the node component
            and jars for all earlier components used, as well as unit tests
            used during the build process.  The unit tests are also working
            examples of how to use the XLattice code.
            </p></td></tr>
        <tr><td>2006-05-21</td>
          <td><strong>transport-0.1.1</strong>
            <p>We add both blocking and non-blocking UDP to the 
              transport component.
            </p></td></tr>
        <tr><td>2006-05-05</td>
          <td><strong>Whoops!</strong>
            <p>There was a serious bug in 0.1.5 making it difficult 
              to run the server.  v0.1.6 of the protocol/stunplus 
              componet went out today.  The 0.1.6 server is running
              on stun.xlattice.org.
        </p></td></tr>
        <tr><td>2006-05-04</td>
          <td><strong>v0.1.5 protocol, STUN+ GUI client releases</strong>
            <p>This is version 0.1.5 of the STUN+/protocol package.
              It corrects bugs reported and makes most enhancements 
              requested through the Sourceforge tracker.  It also adds
              the first elements of the XLattice messaging protocol.
           </p><p>The GUI client now supports encrypted authentication
           using TLS/TCP.  It also allows users to select most of the
           standard STUN servers through a pulldown menu.  We would
           appreciate any further suggestions for GUI client enhancements
           after user experience with the package.
           </p><p>As usual, there are three files in the release:
            protocol-0.1.5.zip, stunplus-0.1.5.zip, and stunplus-current.zip.
        </p></td></tr>
        <tr><td>2006-04-25</td>
          <td><strong>protocol, STUN+ with GUI client releases</strong>
            <p>The 0.1.4 protocol release adds a GUI client and 
              corrects all of the more serious limitations reported
              through the Sourceforge tracker.  We add a facility for
              testing binding lifetime, but this has not been thoroughly
              tested.</p>
            <p>The GUI client should run on any host with a reasonably 
              recent version of Java.  We would appreciate feedback from users.
            </p><p>
            Server discovery is supported in this release but limited to 
            UDP servers in the GUI client.
            </p><p>
            The command line client supports encrypted authentication 
            using TLS.  The GUI client as yet doesn't.
            </p><p>
            As usual, there are three files in the release: 
            protocol-0.1.4.zip, stunplus-0.1.4.zip, and stunplus-current.zip.
        </p></td></tr>
        <tr><td>2006-04-16</td>
          <td><strong>STUN+, protocol releases</strong>
            <p>These are bug-fix releases of the protocol component.  As 
              usual source code is packaged as protocol-0.1.3.zip
              and the binary release is stunplus-0.1.3.zip AKA
              stunplus-current.zip.</p></td></tr>
        <tr><td>2006-04-15</td>
          <td><strong>component releases</strong>
            <p>Because Sourceforge CVS is currently running a couple
              of weeks behind, we put interim releases of several 
              components on Sourceforge today.  These are</p>
              <ul>
                <li>util-0.3.7.tar.gz</li>
                <li>corexml-0.3.3.tar.gz</li>
                <li>crypto-0.1.0.zip</li>
                <li>transport-0.1.0.zip</li>
              </ul>
              <p>All of these have been tested on both Linux (Debian) and
              Windows (XP).  The <strong>util</strong> and 
              <strong>corexml</strong> releases are packaged as tarballs
              solely due to lack of time.  In the next release they will
              be .zip files.
        </p></td></tr>
        <tr><td>2006-04-05</td>
          <td><strong>STUN+ and protocol third releases</strong>
            <p>This is the third set of XLattice protocol releases
              in this series.  It incorporates what is as far as we
              know the first open source version of STUN with TLS-based
              authentication.  As usual, there are three release: source 
              code release as protocol-0.1.2.zip, binary as stunplus-0.1.2.zip, 
              and stunplus-current now mirrors the binary release.
              The binary package should run on any machine with a 
              recent Java run-time (1.4 or better JRE).</p>
            <p>This code has been developed and tested on Debian Linux
              hosts.  There are several known limitations which will
              be documented on the Sourceforge project
              <a href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?group_id=92652">
                tracker</a>.  These will have been corrected and the
              code tested on Windows XP prior to the next release.
            </p>
          </td></tr>
      <tr><td>2006-03-10</td>
        <td><strong>STUN+ and protocol second releases</strong>
          <p>These are the second releases of the XLattice STUN
            client and server.  The source code release is
            protocol-0.1.1.zip.  This is accompanied by a 
            new binary release, stunplus-0.1.1.zip which, as
            before, is mirrored by an update to stunplus-current.zip.
            That is, stunplus-current is now identical to stunplus-0.1.1.</p>
        </td></tr>
      <tr><td>2006-03-07</td>
        <td><strong>STUN+ and protocol releases</strong>
          <p>We published a preliminary release of our STUN client
            and server on Sourceforge today.  The source code was
            released as protocol-0.1.0.zip.  The STUN-specific 
            scripts and documentation plus the jars necessary to
            run the client and server were packaged as two separate
            but identical releases.  The first is stunplus-0.1.0.zip.
            The second is stunplus-current.zip.  This will be kept in
            sync with the current numbered release (0.1.0 at this time).</p>
        </td></tr>
      <tr><td>2006-01-30</td>
        <td><strong>Web site changes</strong>
          <p>The Web site is now being generated using Apache Forrest,
            which has resulted in some glitches.  The process should
            be completed in a week or so.  </p>
          <p>The older version of the Web site continues to be 
            available at <a href="http://www.xlattice.org">
              www.xlattice.org</a> and will remain unchanged for some
            time.</p>
      </td></tr> 
      <tr><td>2005-09-22</td>
        <td><strong>CryptoServer 0.0.11 release</strong>
          <p>
            This is a minor release to fix a small bug that
            has shown up in production use of the server.
          </p>
        </td></tr> 
      <tr><td>2005-03-11</td>
        <td><strong>CryptoServer 0.0.10 release</strong>
          <p>
            This is a major upgrade which is now being used
            to support www.xlattice.org.  That is, 
            xlattice.sourceforge.net runs on Apache, but 
            www.xlattice.org runs on CryptoServer 0.0.10.
            This is a caching server and a secure server:
            pages are loaded by content key, site build lists
            are digitally signed, and the master key is on a
            different machine several thousand miles away.
          </p>
        </td></tr>
      <tr><td>2005-02-15</td>
        <td><strong>CryptoServer 0.0.9 release</strong>
          <p>
            A substantially improved version of the CryptoServer.  
            It now supports HTTP/1.1 GET and HEAD methods and has 
            been tested with a number of domain names.  Most HTTP 
            headers are recognized.
          </p>
        </td></tr>
      <tr><td>2005-02-02</td>
        <td><strong>CryptoServer 0.0.8 release</strong>
          <p>
          This is a tarball release of a minimal server.
          The .zip file includes all jars necessary to run
          the server.  Source is not included with the release,
          except for source for the CryptoServer itself.
          Source for all XLattice components used IS available in CVS.
          </p><p>
          A rudimentary Users Guide is available 
          <a href="applications/httpd/userguide.html">here</a>.
          </p><p>
          In its current form, the CryptoServer software can 
          load a Web site from disk into a cache keyed by content 
          hash and serve that single site.  This is 
          a non-blocking HTTP/0.9 server operating from an
          in-memory cache.
          </p>
        </td></tr>
      <tr><td>2005-01-30</td>
        <td><strong>CryptoServer 0.0.6 prerelease</strong>
          CryptoServer software can now load a Web site from
          disk into a cache keyed by content hash and serve
          that single site.  All of the relevant code is in 
          CVS, including comprehensive unit tests.  This is 
          a non-blocking HTTP/0.9 server operating from an
          in-memory cache.
        </td></tr>
      <tr><td>2005-01-09</td>
        <td><strong>CryptoServer 0.0.4 prerelease</strong>
          Much code for the CryptoServer is now in CVS.  A working
          server is now expected by the end of January.
          For further information see
          the <a href="applications/httpd/roadmap.html">Roadmap.</a>
        </td></tr>
      <tr><td>2004-11-01</td>
        <td><strong>CryptoServer 0.0.1 prerelease</strong>
          Early code is out for XLattice's first application, a 
          high performance secure Web server, a front end to 
          peer-to-peer networks.  For further information see
          the <a href="applications/httpd/roadmap.html">Roadmap.</a>
        </td></tr>
      <tr><td>2004-09-21</td>
        <td><strong>corexml-0.3 release.</strong>
          CoreXml's Java data binding facility has been significantly 
          enhanced.  It now is both capable of converting an XML document 
          to a tree of Java objects and of the reverse operation, 
          generating an XML document from a tree of Java objects 
          conforming to a Mapping.  Documentation for all CoreXml 
          facilities has also been considerably improved. 
      </td></tr>
      <tr><td>2004-09-19</td>
        <td><strong>util-0.3 release.</strong>
        Adds support for Web Start (JNLP) version numbers and 
        brings XLattice Version class in line with this, to 
        allow XLattice components to be distributed using JNLP.
      </td></tr>
      <tr><td>2004-08-13</td>
        <td><strong>projmgr-0.2 release</strong>
          A bugfix release, bringing XLattice's project management
          component up to date with the other two released components,
          util-0.2 and corexml-0.2.
      </td></tr>
      <tr><td>2004-08-13</td>
        <td><strong>corexml-0.2 release</strong>
          Fixes some minor bugs in XLattice's core XML 
          facility and adds the implementation of the corexml.bind 
          package, which enables programmers to automate the creation 
          of Java objects from XML input files.
      </td></tr>
      <tr><td>2004-08-13</td>
        <td><strong>util-0.2 release.</strong>
          This is a minor bugfix release, one of a set of simultaneous
          releases of XLattice components (util-0.2, corexml-0.2, and 
          projmgr-0.2)
      </td></tr>
      <tr><td>2004-08-04</td>
        <td><strong>projmgr-0.1 release.</strong>
          This is a preliminary release of XLattice's ProjMgr component,
          used for management of software development of XLattice and
          similar multi-component projects.  It depends upon the recently 
          released util-0.1 and corexml-0.1 components.

          The release is packaged as a zip file which unzips into a 
          ./xlattice subdirectory.  In addition to packages included 
          with other components, ProjMgr depends upon the Antlr 
          lexer/parser generator, which is included with the distribution.

          Linux/FreeBSD/UNIX users can run unit tests by typing
          <source>
cd xlattice/projmgr
./build.sh test
</source>
      </td></tr>
      <tr><td>2004-07-29</td>
        <td><p><strong>corexml-0.1 release.</strong>  
            This is a preliminary release of the CoreXml component, containing
            XML facilities to be used by most other XLattice components.  It
            depends upon the recently released util-0.1 module.</p>

           <p>The release is packaged as a zip file which unzips into 
             a ./xlattice subdirectory.  Necessary jars, including Ant 
             and JUnit, are included in xlattice/lib.  The corexml-0.1 
             release jar is in xlattice/lib/xlattice.</p>
           
           <p>Linux/FreeBSD/UNIX users can run unit tests by typing</p>

          <source>
cd xlattice/corexml
./build.sh test
</source>
                
        </td></tr>
      <tr><td>2004-07-28</td>
        <td><p><strong>util-0.1 release.</strong>
            This is a preliminary release of
          utilities to be used by most or all
          XLattice components, including the Version superclass and the
          cmdline package.</p>
          <p>The release is packaged as a zip file which unzips into a 
            ./xlattice subdirectory.  Necessary jars, including Ant and JUnit, 
            are included in xlattice/lib.  The util-0.1 release jar is in 
            xlattice/lib/xlattice.  Linux/FreeBSD/UNIX users can run unit 
            tests by typing</p>
          <source>
cd xlattice/util
./build.sh test
</source>
      </td></tr>
      <tr><td>2004-01-12</td>
        <td>Bloom filter implementation (org.xlattice.filters)</td></tr>
      <tr><td>2003-12-21</td>
        <td>implementation plan for p2p file sharing model application
      </td></tr>
    <tr><td>2003-12-11</td>
      <td>description of 
        <a href="nodes/byzantine.html">
          decision-making by authentication server clusters
      </a></td></tr>
  </table>
  </body>
</document>
