<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
      <!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
    <document>

<header><title>Stun</title></header>

<body>
  <section id="overview"><title>Overview</title>
    <p>STUN is fully documented in 
      <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3489.txt">RFC 2782</a>.
      The discussion here provides additional information to ease
      the learning curve.</p>
  </section>
  <section id="protocol"><title>The Protocol</title>
    <p>STUN can be broken down into three parts:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>server discovery</li>
      <li>binding</li>
      <li>shared secrets and authentication</li>
    </ul>
    <section id="server-discovery"><title>Server Discovery</title>
      <p>Server discovery is a procedure for locating the STUN servers
        provided by a particular domain.  It is not essential and seems
        to be little used.</p>

      <p>STUN servers can be discovered through the DNS.  Full details
        can be found in 
        <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2782.txt">RFC 2782</a>
        but a summary is provided here.
      </p>
      <section id="dns-config"><title>DNS Configuration</title>
        <p>In order to configure the service you must have admin
          privileges for the domain name being configured.  The
          exact way of effecting this varies with the name server
          being used.  With BIND you add a line like</p>
        <source>
_stun._udp      SRV  10 0 3478  stun.xlattice.org.
        </source>
        <p>This says that a STUN UDP service is supplied at port 3478
        at stun.xlattice.org.  The <strong>10 0</strong> are the
        priority and weight respectively and are not important if
        only one stun server is on line.</p>
        <p>A second <strong>_stun._tcp</strong> line is necessary if
        the shared secret service part of the protocol is also being
        supplied over a TCP TLS connection.</p>
        <p>Under UNIX/Linux you can query the  availability of one of 
        the services with a line like</p>
        <source>
dig -t SRV _stun._udp.xten.com
        </source>
        <p>The reply will look like</p>
        <source>
_Service._Proto.Name TTL   Class SRV Priority Weight Port Target
_stun._udp.xten.net. 3600    IN  SRV    10      0    3478 xtunnels.xten.net.
        </source>
        <p>We have added the first line to make the layout clear; 
          only the second line will actually appear.</p>
        <p>These records are conventionally attached to an organization's
          top-level domain.  In the case above, for example, the
          service record is attached to <strong>xten.com</strong> 
          rather than say <strong>stun.xten.com</strong>.  This makes
          sense, as the query is in essence "what STUN-udp servers are 
          available in your organization?" and the reply will be a 
          list of available servers, with the <strong>priority</strong>
          and <strong>weight</strong> numbers providing a guide as to
          which should be used.</p>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="binding"><title>Binding</title>
      <p>Binding is another discovery procedure: it enables a client 
        behind a NAT to determine what its public IP address and port
        are, and it allows the client to explore how these change if
        the server's IP address and/or port number change.  This 
        information can be used to guess what kind of NAT the client is
        behind.</p>
      <p>This is the basic STUN service, the one that must be supported
        by any STUN client or server.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="shared-secret"><title>SharedSecret</title>
      <p>If authentication and security are issues, the client can 
        obtain a short-lived shared secret from the server.  This is done 
        over a TCP connection running TLS.  The shared secret can then
        be used to attach an SHA1-HMAC to messages between the client and
        the STUN server.  See
        <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2104.txt">RFC 2104</a>
        for further information on HMACs.
      </p>
      <p>
        Many public servers do not provide this part of the STUN protocol.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="tls"><title>TLS</title>
      <p>TLS is the IETF's version of SSL, the protocol used for secure
        Web connections (https).</p>
      <p>In Java there are two commonly used TLS packages,
        <a href="www.rtfm.com/puretls/">PureTLS</a>
        and 
        <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsse/">JSSE</a>.  
        Tomcat uses these as alternatives, first trying
        to load PureTLS and then looking for JSSE.  
      </p>  
      <p>It appears that PureTLS is no longer being supported.  We
        have as yet not been able to make it work with Java 1.5.
      </p>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="servers"><title>Public STUN Servers</title>
    <p>The table below lists STUN servers that we know to provide
      the basic UDP BindingRequest/Response service.  If the
      <strong>DNS?</strong> column has a Y in it, there is an SRV
      record.  If there is a Y in the <strong>tcp?</strong> column, the
      SRV record claims that they provide the TLS authentication service,
      but we haven't tested this.</p>
    <table>
      <tr><th>domain name</th><th>DNS?</th><th>tcp?</th><th>remarks</th></tr>
      <tr><td>stun.fwdnet.net</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td/></tr>
      <tr><td>stun01.sipphone.com</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td/></tr>
      <tr><td>stun.softjoys.com</td><td>Y</td><td>Y</td><td/></tr>
      <tr><td>stun.voipbuster.com</td><td>N</td><td>?</td><td/></tr>
      <tr><td>stun.voxgratia.org</td><td>N</td><td>?</td>
        <td>SRV record says services not provided</td></tr>
      <tr><td>stun.xten.net</td><td>N</td><td>N</td><td/></tr>
      <tr><td>stun1.noc.ams-ix.net</td><td>Y</td><td>N</td><td/></tr>
    </table>
    <section id="vovida-software"><title>Vovida Software</title>
      <p>The open source C++ STUN server/client code available for 
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=47735">
          download</a>
        is commonly used on the public servers 
        but does not support authentication.
        The tlsServer does not compile.  The udp server returns an
        extension attribute <strong>ServerName</strong> which has a value 
        of "Vovida.org 0.96".</p>
      <p>This software is from a SourceForge project, 
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/stun">
          http://sourceforge.net/projects/stun</a>.
        At the time of writing the project has an open tracker item dated
        2004-04-16 and entitled "support user/password hmac stuff".
     </p>
   </section>
  </section>
</body>
</document>
