<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
      <!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
    <document>
  
    <header><title>P2P File Sharing</title></header>
      
  
  <body>
    <section id="BasicRequirements"><title>Basic Requirements</title>
      <p>Requirements include</p>
      <ul>
        <li><strong>Anonymity</strong> for both those posting material to 
          the system (publishers) and those 
          retrieving material from the system (readers).</li>
        <li><strong>Content Encryption.</strong> All files and all inter-node
          messages should be encrypted.</li>
        <li><strong>Replication and Dispersal.</strong> 
          The system should have some provision
          for automatically copying files and distributing copies
          across the network, so that bringing down
          any one or any small group of servers would be unlikely 
          to remove documents from the system.</li>
        <li><strong>Automatic Migration.</strong>  Files should tend to drift
          towards where they are most used.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section id="FreenetDeficiencies"><title>Freenet Deficiencies</title>
      <p>Freenet in particular has been widely analysed and is known
        to have several deficiencies.  Any new system would have to
        address these.</p>
      <ul>
        <li><strong>Performance.</strong>  Freenet is perceived by many as 
          very slow.</li>
        <li><strong>Authentication.</strong>  Freenet has no mechanism for
          authenticating users.  This leaves it open to a variety
          of denial of service (DOS) attacks.</li>
        <li><strong>Prevention of Flooding.</strong>  Any user can flood 
          Freenet either by inserting bogus content into the 
          system or by requesting content that is far away in 
          network terms.  In the latter case the system will 
          replicate a document copy on every server queried in 
          the course of retrieving the document.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section id="OtherPossibleRequirements"><title>Other Possible Requirements</title>
      <ul>
        <li><strong>Graceful Fragmentation.</strong>  The system should 
          survive network fragmentation.  This might be caused
          by a failure in the underlying Internet or by the loss of
          an excessive number of authentication servers.</li>
        <li><strong>Graceful Merger.</strong>  If a system has survived
          fragmentation, so that it continues to exist as two separate
          networks, then when whatever condition caused the 
          fragmentation changes, it should be possible to remerge
          the two fragments.  Ideally this will occur automatically.</li>
        <li><strong>Graceful Joins.</strong>  From a user's point of view, 
          joining the network should be entirely automatic or very
          nearly so.  </li>
        <li><strong>Graceful Leaving.</strong>  While it should be possible for
          a node to notify the system that it is leaving (being powered 
          down, for example), the system should respond automatically
          to a node's departure.</li>
        <li><strong>Compatibility with Other P2P Networks.</strong>  It is highly
          desirable that XLattice support gateways into other p2p 
          networks such as
          <a href="http://www.freenetproject.org">freenet</a> and 
          <a href="http://mnet.sourceforge.net">mnet.</a></li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
