<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
      <!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
    <document>

<header><title>Httpd</title></header>

<body>
<p>

</p>
<section id="CryptoServer"><title>CryptoServer</title>
  
<p>
XLattice's CryptoServer is a lightweight Web server for the truly
paranoid: nothing is displayed without being authorized and having
its integrity guaranteed, and any user interaction with the server 
can be authenticated and logged.
</p>
  <note>The name <strong>CryptoServer</strong> is provisional.</note>
<p>
The CryptoServer is a daemon which listens for HTTP requests on a 
single port, normally port 80.  When a request is received, the 
daemon first checks the source of the request against a blacklist.  
If there is a match, the connection is silently closed.  Otherwise 
the server checks the
name or IP address to which the request is addressed against a list
of site names.  If there is no match, the connection is dropped.
Otherwise the server checks the file requested against a list for 
that site.  If the file name is not present, the server returns a 
<strong>404</strong>
 message, "file not found".  Otherwise the request is valid 
and the server attempts to return the file
from an in-memory cache.  If the file is not actually present in
memory, the memory cache retrieves it from a disk cache.  If the 
file is not present there, the disk cache retrieves it from another
server, usually using TCP/IP, the standard Internet protocol for 
reliable communications.
</p>
<p>
At each step in the process there are cryptographic checks to 
ensure the integrity of the data being returned.  
</p>
<section id="Hashes"><title>Hashes</title>
<p>
Except where otherwise qualified, by <strong>
hash</strong>
 we mean a 160-bit 
binary value.  This 20-byte value is most often a <strong>
content key,</strong>
 
an SHA-1 digest of a file's contents.  SHA-1 is one of the two 
most commonly used 
algorithms for generating hashes from binary data; the other, MD5,
is believed to be less secure.  SHA-1 is quite widely
used in business and mandated by the US government for use in 
communicating and storing sensitive Federal data.  Like the title keys
discussed below, content keys are guaranteed to be unique: given a
document with a particular SHA-1 digest, it is for all practical 
purposes impossible to find another document with the same digest.
</p>
<p>
<em>
More precisely these hashes are</em>
 <strong>
quasi-unique:</strong>
 <em>
there is a theoretical
possibility that two files or build lists will have the same hash, 
but this is exceedingly unlikely to occur within the lifespan of the 
universe.</em>

</p>
<p>
The other type of XLattice hash is a <strong>
title key.</strong>
   The integrity of a file
with a content key is determined simply by running the SHA-1 
algorithm on its contents: if the result doesn't match the SHA-1
digest that is the basis of the file name, the file has been tampered
with or is otherwise corrupt.  This is good for invariant data but
not where you want to assign the same name to data that changes from
time to time.
</p>
<p>
A title key is an SHA-1 digest obtained from the author's public
key, normally a 1024 bit quantity, and the document title, where the
"title" will most often be a directory name.   The title key 
can identify a single document but more often identifies a particular 
<strong>
build file,</strong>
 a dated and digitally signed list of names and their hashes.  
</p>
<p>
A file is retrieved from disk or the Net using its hash.  The file
is identified in storage by that hash.  In the simplest implementation,
the file name is the hash itself, base-64 encoded.
This scheme encodes 6 bits into a byte, so that 
encoding three bytes of binary data gives you four bytes of printable
ASCII text.  A 20-byte hash therefore encodes into 28 bytes.
</p>
</section>
<section id="CryptographicIdentities"><title>Cryptographic Identities</title>
<p>
In the sense in which we use the term, a cryptographic identity is a
pair of keys.  One of these, the <strong>
public key,</strong>
 is published and so can
be used 
to identify an entity (a human being, XLattice node, authority, whatever).
The other, the <strong>
private key,</strong>
 is held secret.  The owner of the key
pair can use the private key to encrypt data or digitally sign a document.
Using the public key, anyone else can verify that the document was 
signed or encrypted by the author.  Alternatively, anyone can use the
public key to encrypt messages which can only be decrypted by the holder 
of the private key.
</p>
<p>
The security of systems employing such key pairs is assumed to be 
related to the length of the keys, with each additional bit doubling
the cryptographic strength.  Currently keys are usually 1024 bits long.
</p>
<p>
There are two such systems in common use, DSA and RSA.  RSA is generally
used both for digital signatures and for message encryption.  DSA is
normally used only for digital signatures.
</p>
</section>
<section id="MasterDomainMasterKey"><title>Master Domain, Master Key</title>
<p>
When the CryptoServer first boots it is assigned a <strong>
master domain</strong>
 and may 
be assigned a <strong>
master key.</strong>
  These assignments are made either in a 
configuration file or on the command line.
</p>
<p>
The <strong>
master domain</strong>
 is a qualified Internet domain name such as 
<code>
xlattice.org</code>
 or <code>
planetlink.ltd.uk.</code>
  The master domain may not be
a top level domain (TLD) such as <code>
.com, .net,</code>
 or <code>
.org,</code>
 nor may it be
a so-called CCTLD <em>
(country code TLD)</em>
 like <code>
.fr</code>
 or <code>
.de.</code>
  Nor may it
be a domain managed by the national registry like <code>
.co.uk</code>
 or <code>
.ltd.uk.</code>

The domain name must be one managed by whoever operates the CryptoServer.
It can of course be that of the server itself.
</p>
<p>
The <strong>
master key</strong>
 is a RSA public key associated with the master domain.
It can either be set in the CryptoServer configuration file or retrieved
from the Internet domain name system, the global DNS.  The public key 
is normally a 1024-bit value.  This key will be used to validate
digital signatures on configuration files and control messages sent to 
the server.
</p>
<p>
If it is to be obtained from the DNS, the master key must be put in
a text record associated with the master domain
(see <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1035.txt?number=1035">
RFC 1035</a>
).
This will contain a quoted string representing the master key's 
value, base-64 encoded.
</p>
<p>
The private key corresponding to the master key must <strong>
not</strong>
 be present 
on the server.  Specifically, the master key is not the same as the
public key of the XLattice node on the CryptoServer.
</p>
<p>
The public key is made visible in the global DNS by adding a line like
</p>
<source>
www.xlattice.org.  IN TXT "rsa 1234567890...abcdefghijklmnopq 3"</source>
<p>

to the domain's name server configuration file.  This is a <strong>
Resource
Record</strong>
 or <strong>
TXT RR.</strong>
  The value after <em>
rsa</em>
 is a base-64 encoded
RSA public key, the master key.  If the key is 1024 bits (128 bytes), 
then that part of the encoded key is 178 bytes long.
</p>
<p>
By default the master domain is <code>
www.xlattice.org</code>
 and by default the 
master key is the www.xlattice.org public key.
</p>
<p>
Changes to the DNS can take a long time to propagate over the Internet, 
weeks in extreme cases.  Because of this it might sometimes be 
advantageous to reserve a set of names just for announcing keys.
</p>
<source>
key1.xlattice.org.  IN TXT "rsa NNNN...NNNN1 3"
key2.xlattice.org.  IN TXT "rsa NNNN...NNNN2 3"</source>
<p>

</p>
</section>
<section id="FiltersBlacklistsandWhitelists"><title>Filters: Blacklists and Whitelists</title>
<p>
A <strong>
filter</strong>
 consists of a set of IP address ranges 
and a list of domain names.  If the filter is used to reject matching
hosts, it is a <strong>
blacklist.</strong>
  If the filter is used as a basis for 
deciding that a request should be served, it is a <strong>
whitelist.</strong>

</p>
<p>
Address ranges are inclusive:
A source address is in range if it is equal to the low-order IP address 
in the range, the high-order address, or anything in between.
If the filter is a blacklist and the IP address from which a request 
comes is in one of the blacklisted ranges, the connection is silently closed.  
</p>
<p>
Domain names are matched from right to left.  In making the comparison,
names are divided into parts at the dots and only the parts are 
compared.  If a source address contains or equals a blacklisted
domain, the connection is dropped.  So if for example <code>
xyz.com</code>
 were
to be blacklisted, then <code>
xyz.com</code>
 and <code>
abc.xyz.com</code>
 would be rejected,
but <code>
xyz1.com</code>
 and <code>
wxyz.com</code>
 would not be.
</p>
<p>
In the longer run, the intention is to automatically detect abusive 
contacts and add them to the blacklist.  However this functionality
will not be implemented soon.
</p>
<p>
The blacklist is loaded when the daemon boots.  The blacklist is 
digitally signed using the SHA1withRSA algorithm, which uses 
the CryptoServer's master key.
</p>
</section>
<section id="SiteList"><title>Site List</title>
<p>
A <strong>
site list</strong>
 is a build file (see below) containing a list of domain names.
The site list is 
signed using the private key corresponding to the CryptoServer's master key.
</p>
<p>
The site list is a list of the Web sites supported by the CryptoServer.
</p>
<p>
The title of the site list is <strong>
site.cfg.</strong>
  Given this title and the
RSA public key, it is straightforward to determine the title key of
the site list and retrieve it, if it is not otherwise available.
</p>
</section>
<section id="BuildFiles"><title>Build Files</title>
<p>
A <strong>
build file</strong>
 consists of
</p>
<ul>
<li>
  a title line
</li>
<li>
  a line holding the base-64 encoded public key of the signer
</li>
<li>
  a timestamp 
</li>
<li>
  zero or more data lines containing the extended hash of a file followed
      by the path to the file relative to the title
</li>
<li>
  a blank line
</li>
<li>
  and a digital signature
</li>
</ul>
<p>
Each line is CRLF-terminated.  That is, each line ends with an ASCII-13
character (carriage return) followed by ASCII-10 (line feed).
</p>
<p>
The title line is commonly a UNIX-style path using a single slash ('/')
as the separator.   The path is <strong>
not</strong>
 terminated with a separator.
</p>
<p>
If the build file represents a subdirectory tree, then the path is 
prepended to the file names in the data lines.  Each such name is 
a path relative to the title and must begin with a UNIX-style separator,
a forward slash ('/').
</p>
<p>
If the build file represents a site list, the title line is the path
to the directory containing the build files for each site.
</p>
<p>
The digital signature is generated from the concatenated title,
public key, timestamp, and data lines, if any, including their 
terminating CRLFs.
</p>
<p>
The build file itself has a hash, the <strong>
title key.</strong>
  
This is the SHA-1 digest of a function 
of the title and the signer's public key.  Because of the way in which
the hash is calculated (it is independent of the timestamp, content,
and digital signature line), this is a permanent, globally unique identifier 
for the build list.  When XLattice key-based storage systems are presented
with a candidate replacement for a build list, they should only replace
the existing build file under its title key if
</p>
<ul>
<li>
  the replacement has the same owner (public key line) and title
</li>
<li>
  the replacement has a valid digital signature
</li>
<li>
  and the replacement has a more recent time stamp
</li>
</ul>
<p>
Current build lists are stored twice, once by title key and once by
content key.  When the build list is replaced by a newer list, the
version stored by title key is replaced, but not the version 
stored by content key.
</p>
</section>
<section id="In-memoryCache"><title>In-memory Cache</title>
<p>
The CryptoServer should normally serve Web pages from its in-memory
cache.  The cache should be large enough so that most (say 90% or 
more) requested pages are in it.  The cache is read-through, meaning
that if a page is not found it is read into the cache before being
served.  Pages are always served from the cache.
</p>
<p>
If the cache fills up, infrequently used pages are dropped from the 
cache using an <strong>
LRU</strong>
 (least recently used) algorithm.
</p>
</section>
<section id="DiskCache"><title>Disk Cache</title>
<p>
Pages not found in the in-memory cache are fetched from the disk
cache manager.  Any page retrieved is always subject to an integrity
check.  If it has a content hash, the disk manager first reads the
file into memory and then takes an SHA-1 hash of its contents, verifying
the SHA-1 hash against the content hash.  If the file is a build list,
</p>
<ul>
<li>
  its hash (a function of public key and title) is verified
</li>
<li>
  and then its digital signature is verified
</li>
</ul>
<p>
In either case, if verification succeeds, the file is passed to the in-memory 
cache manager.  Otherwise the file is discarded and the disk file deleted.
</p>
<p>
In such cases and also where the file is simply not present in the disk
cache, the data is retrieved from the network using the hash as a
key.  The disk cache is also read-through and managed using an LRU
algorithm:
data retrieved from the Net will be written to disk before being
passed to the memory cache manager, and if there is insufficient
room, the least recently used data on the disk will be removed to
make room for the new data.
</p>
</section>
<section id="RetrievalfromtheNet"><title>Retrieval from the Net</title>
<p>
Where a file is not found in the disk cache, it is fetched from
the Net using its hash as a key.  The Web site's owner, the signer 
of the build list, will normally be an XLattice Peer of the 
CryptoServer.
</p>
<p>
It is likely that for most early applications the entire Web site will
be loaded directly into the CryptoServer's disk cache or will 
be fetched from a single backing server.  However, as XLattice's 
routing protocols are developed, it will become possible for 
the server to fetch files by key from arbitrarily complex networks.
</p>
</section>
<section id="HTTPProtocolVersionSupport"><title>HTTP Protocol Version Support</title>
<p>
CryptoServer will first support HTTP/0.9, then HTTP/1.0 as defined
by 
<a href="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc1945.html">
RFC 1945</a>
, 
and then HTTP/1.1 as specified in 
<a href="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc2616.html">
RFC 2616</a>
. 
More 
detailed information on the implementation plan can be found in the
<a href="roadmap.html">
Roadmap</a>
.
</p>
</section>
<section id="Dependencies"><title>Dependencies</title>
<p>
The server software depends upon a number of XLattice components
and other jars.
At the time of writing these are
</p>
<ul>
<li>
  util-0.3.<strong>
x</strong>
.jar
</li>
<li>
  xpp3-1.1.3.4.C.jar
</li>
<li>
  corexml-0.3.x.jar
</li>
<li>
  crypto-0.0.<strong>
x</strong>
.jar
</li>
<li>
  node-0.0.<strong>
x</strong>
.jar
</li>
<li>
  protocol-0.0.<strong>
x</strong>
.jar
</li>
<li>
  overlay-0.0.<strong>
x</strong>
.jar
</li>
</ul>
<p>
The 'x' in the XLattice component version number 
is currently 1 in each case, but this will be changing 
frequently as implementation progresses.  The xpp3 jar is an 
<a href="http://www.extreme.indiana.edu/xgws/xsoap/xpp/">
XML pull parser.</a>

</p>
<p>
Current jars for all dependencies will be included
in the CryptoServer distribution, excepting only Java's runtime
libraries.
</p>
</section>
<section id="Security"><title>Security</title>
<p>
Because the private keys used to sign build files should not be 
present on the CryptoServer, it should not be possible to modify
the server's configuration or any of the files being served without
this being detected.  When the server detects that a file has been
modified, it will attempt to replace it from a secure source.  If
it cannot, it will either do nothing (fail to respond to the request)
or shut down entirely.
</p>
<p>
This means that the server should be secure 
against all but very determined attackers with very large resources.
If the attacker has complete control of the server and the necessary
technical skills, he or she could simply replace the server or its
software entirely.
However, it is very likely that this would be quickly detected.
</p>
<p>
More subtle changes would require compromising the keys used to sign
configuration files.  This is for all practical purposes impossible
so long as the operator of the CryptoServer takes realistic steps
to safeguard the physical security of these keys.
</p>
<p>

</p>
</section>
</section>
</body>
</document>
