<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
      <!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header><title>Components</title></header>
  
  <body>
    <p>Further information on the components described below can be
      found by selecting from the menu to the left.  Sourcecode and
      API links are to the Java implemtation; the C++ code is handled 
      separately.
    </p>
    
    <section id="released">
      <title>Already Released or About To Be Released</title>
      <p>
      XLattice currently has five separately-released Java components:
      </p>
      
      <ul>
        <li><strong>util-0.3.7</strong></li>
        <li><strong>corexml-0.3.3</strong></li>
        <li><strong>crypto-0.1.0</strong></li>
        <li><strong>transport-0.1.1</strong></li>
        <li><strong>protocol-0.1.6</strong></li>
        <li><strong>node-0.1.0</strong></li>
      </ul>

      <p>In each case the next decimal version is available in CVS.
       So for example util-0.3.8 is currently in CVS at Sourceforge.</p>
     
      <p>The releases can be downloaded by clicking on the 
        <strong>other downloads</strong>
        button in the menu bar at the left of this screen.  
        Some are currently packaged as UNIX <strong>tarballs</strong>
        (files with .tar.gz extensions) but all will be
        packaged as zip files in future.</p>
      
      <p>All releases include comprehensive unit test software and
        all jars necessary to run the tests.  This means that 
        <strong>each component release includes jars for any other
          XLattice components used</strong>.  Each is also a source code 
        release, except that <strong>protocol</strong> is accompanied by
        a <strong>stun+</strong> binary release with the same version
      number.</p>
    </section>
    
    <section id="cryptoServer">
      <title>Components Released with CryptoServer</title>
      
      <p>For some time development effort was focused on the
      <a href="/applications/httpd/index.html">CryptoServer,</a>
      a secure Web server being built from XLattice components.  
      Like the component releases, the CryptoServer tarball includes
      all jars necessary to run it.
    </p>

    <p>In addition to the components listed above, the CryptoServer
      uses:</p>
    
    <table>
        <tr><td><strong>overlay</strong></td><td>0.0.1</td>
          <td><code>DataKeyed, NameKeyed</code> 
            key-based message routing</td></tr>
        <tr><td><strong>node</strong></td><td>0.0.4</td>
          <td>reads configuration files, orchestrates node functions</td></tr>
        <tr><td><strong>httpd</strong></td><td>0.0.1</td>
          <td>Web server (HTTP) functionality</td></tr>
      </table>

      <p>At the time of writing, the source code in CVS for these
        components is the most recent source code.</p>
      
      <p>For more specific information on the CryptoServer, see the
      <a href="../applications/httpd/roadmap.html">
      CryptoServer development roadmap.</a> </p>
  </section>
  <section id="cpp"><title>C++ Implementation</title>
    <p>The discussion above relates to XLattice's Java implementation.
      C++ work is being handled separately.  Further information will
      be available shortly, when a C++ tab will appear at the top of
      this page.</p>
  </section>
  </body>
</document>
