<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
      <!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
    <document>
  
    <header><title>Nodes</title></header>
      
  
  <body>
      <section id="Nodes"><title>Nodes</title>
      <p>An XLattice node is a network component that can send and 
        receive messages and has some (potentially shared) local 
        store.  The node has unique identifier and one or more 
        addresses.</p>
      
      <p>A node identifier, its <strong>nodeID</strong>, is a 160-bit
        number chosen by a crypto-strength random number generator.
        While it is theoretically possible for two nodes to have the
        same nodeID, it is not likely that this will occur within the 
        lifetime of the universe.</p>
        
      <p>A node's address is one at which it can be reached 
        through an overlay to which the node is connected.  This 
        might be, or might contain, an Internet
        Protocol (IP) address and port number.
      </p>
      <section id="NodeTypes"><title>Node Types</title>
        <p>An XLattice network is built from nodes of various types.
          The most fundamental type is a client which connects 
          a user to one or more lattices, networks.  The client
          may either create its own network (lattice)  
          or may join an existing one.
          The first time that it joins a lattice it must get a node ID from the
          network's authentication servers.
        </p>
        <table>
          <tr><th>node type</th><th>connectivity</th><th>description</th></tr>
          <tr><td><a href="client.html">client</a></td><td>1:N</td>
            <td>connects a single user to the network</td></tr>
          <tr><td><a href="server.html">server</a></td><td>N:1 or N:M</td>
            <td>maintains persistent shared storage 
              for a group of nodes; such servers may be replicated</td></tr>
          <tr><td><a href="byzantine.html">consensus</a></td><td>N:1, M:M</td>
            <td>a specialized server, one of a cluster, 
              the M members of which authenticate 
              decisions by voting among themselves using
              Byzantine protocols</td></tr>
          
          <tr><td><a href="broker.html">broker</a></td><td>N:N</td>
            <td>routes messages according to network policy,
              possibly doing protocol translation</td></tr>
          <tr><td><a href="filter.html">filter</a></td><td>1:1</td>
            <td>filters messages according to local policy</td></tr>
        </table>
      </section>
      <section id="NodesvsPlatforms"><title>Nodes vs Platforms</title>
        <p>Nothing prohibits there being several types of node on one
          platform.  It is expected that some XLattice resources will
          be more permanent and widely shared, and that some smaller 
          and more transient groups of users will organize themselves
          into small groups (lattices).  In such small groups the
          server nodes supporting persistence and certifying 
          identities would run on user machines.
        </p>
      </section>
    </section> 
  </body>
</document>
